信中所写何事
What does this letter say?
想必陛下业已读过
I thought Your Majesty just read
我要你亲口告诉我
I asked you to tell me what this letter says,
赫福德大人
my Lord Hertford.
信中指控凯瑟琳王后
The letter accuses Queen Katherine of dissolute living
在婚前生活放荡
before she was married to Your Majesty,
居于诺福克公爵遗孀宅邸期间
while she was living with the Dowager Duchess of Norfolk.
曾有两名男子
There was two men.
一位是音乐教师亨利·麦诺士
A music teacher named Henry Manox,
还有一位弗朗西斯·迪尔罕先生
and a gentleman called Francis Dereham.
她的作风人尽皆知
And that her way of life was not a secret,
放荡不已
that many knew of it.
是谁写的信
Who wrote the letter?
这是封匿名信
It is not signed.
寄信人声称之所以采用如此方式
Whoever left the letter says he only wrote
是因为他没脸当面告诉国王陛下
it because he did not have the heart to tell you by mouth.
这肯定是凭空捏造
It's a forgery!
是的 陛下
Yes, Your Majesty.
这种指控是恶意诽谤
The accusations in this letter are maliciously intended.
树大招风 难免如此
Many calumnies are published about well-known persons,
不是吗
are they not?
- 是的 陛下 - 不管怎样 大人
- Yes, Your Majesty. - Nevertheless, my Lord,
我命你彻查此事
I charge you to investigate the matter thoroughly.
定要不惜一切代价 查个水落石出
Do not desist until you have reached to the bottom of the pot.
- 是 陛下 - 在此期间
- Majesty. - In the meantime, the Queen shall be confined
将王后软禁于寝宫 由罗彻福德女士照管
to her apartments, with only Lady Rochford in attendance
直至此事查清为止
until her name is cleared.
退下吧
My Lord.
陛下 告退
Majesty.
陛下
Your Majesty.
不 给我另一只手
No, the other hand.
怎么了
What?
卫队长 这算什么
Sergeant? What is this?
陛下 国王下令
My Lady, you are confined to your apartments,
于现在起 您被软禁于此
with only Lady Rochford to attend you,
仅有罗彻福德女士照看您
for as long as it please the King.
- 不 - 不要 凯瑟琳
- No! - Please, Katherine!
- 琼 - 快阻止他们
- Joan! - Don't let them take me!
琼
Joan! Joan!
为什么 为何待我如此
Why? Why must I stay here?
求你告诉我 我不明白
Please tell me. I don't understand.
请原谅 陛下
Forgive me, my Lady.
从现在开始 门外会有卫兵看守
But from now on there will be a guard posted just beyond the door.
求你了
Please.
弗朗西斯·迪尔罕 你被捕了
Francis Dereham, you are under arrest.
为什么
Under arrest for what?
我问你 凭什么逮捕我
For what, I ask you?
我要问你一些问题
I want to ask you some questions
有关几年前
about what went on, some years ago,
发生在朗伯斯的一些事
at Lambeth,
当时的凯瑟琳·霍华德
between Katherine Howard, as she then was,
她和这两个男人
and two men:
亨利·麦诺士和弗朗西斯·迪尔罕
Henry Manox and Francis Dereham.
你很清楚我在说什么吧
You know what I'm talking about, don't you?
你不必害怕 布尔默女士
There's no need to be afraid, Mistress Bulmer.
只要你如实相告
No harm will come to you
我便不会伤害你
so long as you tell me the truth!
你明白了吗
Is that clear?
是的 大人
Yes, sir.
这个叫亨利·麦诺士的男人
I understand that this man,
他是个音乐老师吗
Henry Manox, was a music teacher?
你是否见过或听过
Did you ever see him
他和凯瑟琳·霍华德行过苟且之事
or hear of him taking liberties with Katherine Howard?
是的 大人 他告诉我 他爱她
Yes, sir. He told me he was in love with her.
我也告诉他
I told him,
若是被诺福克公爵夫人发现
I said if my lady of Norfolk knew of the love between him
肯定不会同意
and Mistress Howard, she would undo him,
因为她出身贵族
because she is from a noble house,
你们门不当户不对 不能成婚
and if you marry her, some of her blood will kill you.
那麦诺士怎么说
And what did Manox say?
管好你的嘴 傻女人
He said, "Hold your peace, woman! My designs are
我欲行苟且之事 不达目的不罢休
"of a dishonest kind. I doubt not I shall achieve my purpose."
她说愿献给他处女之身
She said to him that he would have her maidenhead,
尽管初失贞洁之痛难忍
though it be painful to her,
但日后定能幸福圆满
knowing he'd be good to her afterwards.
那他是否拥有了她的处女之身
And did he...have her maidenhead?
没有 大人 当时她又另有所爱
No, sir, for she started seeing someone else.
是弗朗西斯·迪尔罕吗
And would that man be Francis Dereham?
是的 大人
Yes, my Lord.
你与凯瑟琳·霍华德相识于朗伯斯吗
Did you know Katherine Howard at Lambeth,
当时她尚值及笄之年
when she was 14 or 15 years old?
是的 大人
Yes, sir.
你与她可曾行过男女之事
Did you have carnal knowledge of her?
我们玩了几次游戏
We-played some games.
装扮成丈夫与妻子
We pretended to be man and wife.
她很开心
It amused her.
你与她是否有过肌肤之亲
Did you know her carnally?
要知道 迪尔罕先生
You should know, Mr. Dereham,
我们已询问过一些佣人
that we have spoken to some of the maids
她们当时与王后同为室友
who used to sleep in the same dormitory.
她们说你曾潜入王后的温床
They say that you crept into the Queen's bed for
多达上百次 甚至更多
a hundred nights or more.
她当时并非王后
She was not the Queen.
我再问一次
Let me ask again.
你与凯瑟琳·霍华德可曾行过男女之事
Did you have carnal knowledge of Katherine Howard?
不
No!
我认为你对我极不坦诚 迪尔罕先生
I thought you were not altogether honest with me, Mr. Dereham.
所以我想让你见识下
I wanted to show you what we do to people who are dishonest.
我们如何处置那些不诚不信之徒
Who don't tell the truth.
我说实话
I'll tell you the truth.
有人对王后提出了某种指控
Certain accusations have been made against the Queen.
何种指控
What kind of accusations?
说她进宫之前
Oh, that she was light, immoral, dissolute...
曾与某些男人
with certain men...
有过轻浮 淫荡 风流之事
before she came to court.
我并不相信
I can't believe it to be true.
但所谓空穴不来风
But since the accusations are made,
我必须知晓真相
I must know all the facts.
现在调查已经展开
But since this inquisition is in progress,
你与人说话时要多加留意
be careful who you speak to.
我不允许有风言风语诋毁她的名声
I'll have no spark of scandal against her name.
遵命 陛下
Yes, Your Majesty.
手气不错
I have a good hand.
他们知道了什么
What do they know?
为何要如此软禁我
Why have I been confined like this?
我不知道
I don't know.
一定说了出去
Someone has told them something!
是谁
Who?
他说了什么
What has he told them?
他到底说了什么
你如此痛哭流涕是为哪般
Why are you crying like this?
此事与你并无相关
It's not about you!
我得跟他谈谈
I have to speak to him.
我得跟陛下谈谈
I have to speak to the King.
他会理解的
He'll understand.
我们有证据证明 凯瑟琳·霍华德
We have some evidence that Katherine Howard gave
曾赠与你一条金链及一顶贵族帽
you a gold chain and rich cap, as a gift.
她为何要赠你如此贵重之礼
Why did she buy you such gifts?
因为当时她爱我
Because she loved me.
当时爱你
Loved you?
是的 大人
Yes, my Lord.
她说过 "我发誓"
She told me: "I promise you
"全心全意地爱着你"
"I do love you with all my heart."
她曾以信仰和婚约为证
She promised by her faith and troth
发誓此生只愿执我之手
that she would take no other husband but me.
如此说来 你们订过婚了
You were pre-contracted then?
是的 大人
Yes, sir.
当时我们都坚信我们会成婚
It was understood between us that we would get married.
所以
That's why...
所以你与她有过肌肤之亲了
That's why you knew her carnally?
是的 大人
Yes, sir.
当时我们并未觉得有何不妥
We didn't think we were doing anything wrong.
她将为我妻 而我将为她夫
She was going to be my wife and I her husband.
我们曾在上帝面前发誓
We'd made promises before God.
那你为何没娶她
Why did you not marry her, then?
有一阵子 我离开朗伯斯去了爱尔兰
I left Lambeth for a while and went to Ireland.
当我回来时 凯瑟琳已在宫中了
When I returned, Katherine was already at court.
王后近来将你召回 雇为她用
The Queen recently took you back into her employment.
有何缘由
On what grounds?
公爵夫人心地善良 对我的才能赞赏有加
The Dowager Duchess was kind enough to speak highly of my talents.
你承认在王后嫁给国王之前
You have admitted to the fact that you had carnal knowledge
曾与她有过肌肤之亲
of the Queen before her marriage to the King.
那他们成婚后 你与她可否还有过不轨之事
But did you also know her carnally afterwards?
没有 大人 我以名誉担保
No, sir! No! On my honour!
你何来名誉 迪尔罕先生
On your honour, Mr. Dereham?
女士
My Lady?
大使大人来了
His Excellency is here.
尤斯塔斯 请坐
Eustace! Please, sit.
谢谢 玛丽女士
Thank you, Lady Mary.
您真是慷慨热情
You are too gracious.
我得见您
I had to see you.
宫中有些谣传
There are many rumours at court.
看来王后已被软禁在她的寝宫
And it seems the Queen has been confined to her apartments.
为何
Why?
无人知晓 但谣传是因她行为不检
Nobody knows. But the rumours speak of her misconduct.
果然不出所料
I knew it.
我就知道她一直都是个轻浮的小淫娃
I knew she was always a light young woman,
终日只知寻欢作乐
dedicated only to pleasure.
悲哀的是 玛丽女士
And the sad fact is, Lady Mary,
霍华德家族都是虔诚的天主教徒
that the Howards are a great Catholic family.
不 尤斯塔斯
No, Eustace,
悲哀的是 凯瑟琳·霍华德
the sad fact is that Katherine Howard was never
从来就不是虔诚的天主教徒 也绝非贤妻
a good Catholic, nor ever a good wife.
更不配为后
Nor even less a Queen!
有何发现
What have you discovered?
凯瑟琳·霍华德是个荡妇
Katherine Howard was a loose young woman.
你明明早就知道
You surely knew that!
我只听说她受非传统教育
I was told that her upbringing had been unconventional.
并不知道有多不传统
I didn't know how unconventional.
我没想到她十四岁时
I didn't suspect that at fourteen years old
就与两个男人初尝云雨了
she was sleeping with two older men!
你也见过她
You met her!
瞧她那魅惑的眼神 清白才怪
You saw the look in her eyes. She was never innocent.
这世道还有谁是清白的呢 亲爱的
And who is innocent, my sweetheart?
迪尔罕招认了什么
What did Dereham confess?
只承认他在王后婚前曾与她有过肌肤之亲
Only that he'd slept with the Queen before she was married.
你相信吗
Do you believe him?
我不知道 我得再问一次
I don't know. I may ask again.
夫君 您要当心
Husband, you must be careful.
别忘了 当时正是是你
If you remember, you were among those
把凯瑟琳·霍华德献给国王
who offered Katherine Howard up to the King.
你以为我不记得吗
Do you suppose I ever forget that?
所以我比其他人都要生气
But that's why I must be harder on her than anyone else.
因为我是被骗的最惨
Since I was the most deceived.
我得去休息了 白天还要干活儿呢
I must to bed. I have things to do in the morning.
我祝愿你们 你们三人 晚安
I bid thee, all three of thee, good night.
晚安 我的兄弟
Good night, brother.
我说
So...
托马斯 给你的孩子取什么名字好呢
what shall we call your child, Thomas?
爱德华大人
Sir Edward
你能告诉我发生什么事吗
can you not tell me what's happening?
求你了 没人向我透露半点风声
I beg you. No one tells me anything.
- 求求你了 - 王后 我不能和您说话
- Please... please... - Madam, I am forbidden to talk to you.
不 你必须告诉我
No, no. You must speak to me.
陛下 不行 那会掉脑袋的
Madam, I can't... On my life!
就说一点
Just something!
我为何被囚于此
Why am I confined here?
出现了什么流言
What has anyone said?
他们已将迪尔罕收监
They have taken Dereham to the Tower.
也抓了公爵遗孀身边的几个侍女
Also some of the maids who attended the Dowager Duchess.
我的天啊
Oh... my God.
我所知仅止于此
That's all I know.
王后 恕臣失礼
Now, Madam, you will have to excuse me.
我只能言尽于此
I can say no more.
国王驾到
His Majesty the King.
陛下
Your Majesty.
- 陛下 - 陛下
- Your Majesty. - Your Majesty.
主教大人
Your Grace?
国王陛下
Your Majesty,
赫福德大人和其他议员
my Lord Hertford, and other Councillors,
对王后通奸一案
have made diligent inquiries
已进行勤力调查
into the question of the misconduct of the Queen.
结果如何
And?
陛下
Your Majesty
不得不禀告陛下
I have to tell Your Majesty that,
虽然只是初步调查
even from my preliminary investigations,
但我们相信 对于凯瑟琳王后的指证
we believe the allegations against Queen Katherine
证据确凿
have a sound basis in fact...
王后与诺福克公爵的遗孀同住时
The Queen received the attentions of her music master,
引起其音乐教师亨利·麦诺士的关注
Henry Manox, when she lived with the Dowager Duchess of Norfolk.
麦诺士发誓王后并未对自己献身
Manox swears under oath that she never gave him her maidenhead...
但与王后有染的人名叫弗朗西斯·迪尔罕
but that instead it was given to a man called Francis Dereham.
有足够的证据证明
There is ample proof that
他们曾多次共度良宵
they spent many nights together...
裸裎相对
naked.
迪尔罕称他曾与王后有过婚约
Dereham claims that he was pre-contracted to the Queen,
所以与其亲热无可厚非
so he did no wrong by having carnal relations with her,
后来这段关系也随着
and that their relationship was over when he left
他去爱尔兰以及王后进宫而结束
for Ireland and the Queen for Your Majesty's court.
不幸的是
Unfortunately...
凯瑟琳王后又将这个迪尔罕
Queen Katherine took this same Dereham
在陛下繁忙之时召回王庭
back into her employment during Your Majesty's late progress,
并任命她为私人文书和侍从
appointing him her personal secretary and usher.
不得不说 她心中对陛下已是不忠
I have to say that she has betrayed you in thought
若非受时机所限
and if she had an opportunity
或许已然令陛下蒙羞了
would have betrayed you in deed.
王后陛下
My Lady.
托马斯大人
Sir Thomas?
有什么事
What is it?
王后 我来向您宣旨
Madam, I have come to tell you that
您犯了欺君之罪
for your offences against the King,
您的一切物品将被抄没
all your household has been discharged.
您的财产和箱柜将被查封和看管
Your coffers and chests will be sealed and placed under guard,
我来此还要没收您的珠宝首饰
and I am also come here to collect all your jewels
将其归还国王
and return them to His Majesty.
托马斯大人 求你别这么做
Please, Sir Thomas... Everything in here is...
陛下在哪儿 我要见他
where is the King? I must see him.
王后 我必须告诉您 鉴于您的罪行
Madam, I must tell you that the King and his Council
国王和议会已商定
have ordained that, for your offences,
撤销您的王后封号
you have forfeited the title of Queen,
降为凯瑟琳·霍华德夫人
and must be known as Lady Katherine Howard.
您今天将被遣往希昂教堂
You will be taken to Syon Abbey today,
若无国王旨意不得回宫
to wait upon the King's further pleasure.
陛下在哪儿
Where is the King?
我要和他谈谈
I need to speak to him.
你不明白 我要和他谈谈
You don't understand. I have to speak to him.
谈过就没事了
Then everything will be all right.
你知道吗 只要谈过就好了
Don't you understand? Everything will be all right.
陛下在小教堂
His Majesty is at Chapel.
但恐怕他不想和你谈
But I fear he will not speak to you.
凯瑟琳夫人
Lady Katherine!
- 拦住她 来人啊 - 凯瑟琳·霍华德 站住
- Stop her! Guards! - Katherine Howard! Stop!
凯瑟琳·霍华德 站住 你被捕了
Katherine Howard! Stop! You are arrested.
站住 别再跑了
Stop! Do not proceed!
- 凯瑟琳·霍华德 - 陛下
- Katherine Howard! - Your Majesty!
我要和你谈谈 求求你了 陛下
I must speak to you. Please, please, Your Majesty!
是我啊 是凯瑟琳
Please, it's me... Katherine! It's Katherine.
是凯瑟琳啊 求你了
It's Katherine. Please. Please.
亨利 求求你
Henry! Henry, please!
不 陛下
No! Your Majesty!
不要啊
No, please!
亨利 不 救救我 亨利
Henry! No, please! Please, Henry!
救我
Please!
莱斯利
Risley. Risley!
陛下
Majesty.
去请加德纳主教
Go and fetch Bishop Gardiner.
- 我有话对他说 - 是 陛下
- I must speak to him. - Yes, Your Majesty.
为什么要这样
Why are you doing this?
为什么这么对我
我已经都招了
I've already told you everything I know!
抓住他的手
His hands, my loves. His hands.
你们要干什么 不要 不
What are you going to do to me? No! No!
不 不 不
No! No! No!
不要啊
NO!
主教大人
Your Grace.
我必须告诉您
I must warn Your Grace
自从这可怜的女子来到此处
that the poor creature, ever since she came here,
便一直痛哭流涕 抑郁悲伤
has been in such lamentation and heaviness
我从未见过有人如此
that I never saw in any creature.
有时她会陷入疯狂
Sometimes in a frenzy, that I had
我不得不卸下可能会伤害到她的器具
to remove every implement that might have harmed her.
凯瑟琳女士
Lady Katherine!
凯瑟琳女士 加德纳主教来看望你了
Lady Katherine! Bishop Gardiner is come to see you.
凯瑟琳女士
Lady Katherine?
凯瑟琳女士 莫要悲泣
Lady Katherine, do not weep,
我带来了陛下的手谕
for I am come here with a letter from His Majesty
承蒙皇恩浩荡 你已获得宽大处理
which offers you his most gracious mercy.
女士 国王已宽谅于你
Madam, the King offers you mercy.
什么
What?
你说什么
What did you say?
这是陛下的手谕
Here is His Majesty's letter.
谕中明示 不管你曾经
In it, he offers you mercy,
做过何等奸龊欺君之事 陛下均可宽谅
despite the...uh...grievous offences you have committed against him,
只要你能如实供认你的罪责
if you will only openly confess your faults.
这里 看到了吗
There. You see?
贱妾恭谢 吾王隆恩
I humbly thank the King,
陛下对贱妾 宽厚慈德
who has shown me more grace and mercy
恩重如山
than I could have hoped for.
但首先 我得问你几个问题
But, first, I must ask you some questions.
如同在审判之日供认一般
And you must answer as truthfully and honestly
你必须如实作答
as you will reply at the Day of Judgement.
凯瑟琳
Katherine!
陛下既已对你宽怀
The King offers his hand in mercy.
便无须再如此惶乱不堪
There is nothing to be frightened of.
冷静 坐下
Come. Come! Sit down.
吾主隆恩 赐妾得以偷生
Alas, my Lord, that I am alive!
惶念死亡恐惧的悲痛
The fear of death does not grieve me as much
远不及愧念罪失君宠的悲伤
as the remembrance of the King's goodness,
尤念及妾身怀有王子之时所受万般宠幸
for when I remember how gracious and loving a Prince
不禁泪雨潸然
I had, I cannot but sorrow.
贱妾本自知罪无可恕
But this sudden mercy,
今日竟幸得陛下宽谅之恩
more than I could have looked for,
念及往日种种 欺君失德之行
makes my offences appear to my eyes
贱妾倍感悔恨 无地自容
more heinous than they did before.
你承认与弗朗西斯·迪尔罕
You confess that this Francis Dereham came
曾在朗伯斯常私会你于闺中吗
often to your bed at Lambeth?
是的 主教大人 他来与我共寝
Yes, my Lord. He has lain with me,
时而衣冠整齐 时而一丝不挂
sometimes in his doublet and hose, and sometimes naked,
我的意思是 并非
but I mean, not so naked
一丝不挂而来 常是衣冠整齐而来
that he had nothing upon him, for he had always
随后便脱得
his doublet on; but I mean
一丝不挂
naked when his hose was pulled down.
是为了满足你们的肉欲吗
In order to know you carnally?
你们之间可有婚约在先
Was there a pre-contract between you?
你曾有意要嫁给他吗
Did you intend to marry him?
当我们在一起的时候
He sometimes called me "Wife" When we were together,
也曾以"夫妻"相称
and I called him "Husband."
然而我认为那并非婚约
Still... I think it was no contract.
如果你们之间存有婚约
If there was a contract,
那么你和陛下的婚姻便无效
then your marriage to the King would be invalid
你虽然会背负失德之耻
you might face shame...
但不会有性命之忧了
but you would not forfeit your life.
他虽许诺会爱我一生一世
He promised to love me with all his heart...
但我仍觉得那不代表婚约
but I think it was no contract.
在你成为王后以后
Did Dereham have carnal knowledge
迪尔罕可曾再与你偷欢寻情
of you after you became Queen?
没有 主教大人 从未有过
No, my Lord. He never did.
我即刻动身返往伦敦
I will go back to London and draft
为你起草一份求情书呈交陛下
a plea of forgiveness for you to submit to the King.
请等一下
Wait!
我仍有要事未说
I have important things to say.
王后请讲
My Lady?
我从未同意与迪尔罕发生肉体关系
I never consented to sex with Francis Dereham.
是他再三纠缠 逼我就范的
He used importunate force against me.
用暴力的方式
In a manner-violence.
他强暴了你吗
He raped you?
王后招供了吗
The Queen confessed?
是的 她说迪尔罕强暴了她
Yes. She told me that Dereham raped her.
如同她所做的其他供述一样
I'm sure she was lying as
在这件事上 无疑她也撒了谎
I'm sure she's lying about other things too.
但是我相信他们之前确实有过
But I do believe that there was some form of pre-contract
某种形式的婚约 这样她与陛下的婚姻便属无效
between them, which would invalidate the marriage.
她也声称自己婚后一直洁身自好吗
And she claims to be innocent after the marriage?
她当然那样说
Of course.
你相信吗
And you believed that?
你不相信吗
You don't believe it?
反正我对迪尔罕所说的一概不信
I don't believe anything Dereham says.
也许不是和迪尔罕呢
It might not be Dereham.
大人何出此言
Why does Your Grace say that?
你拿到王后的供词了吗
You have the Queen's confession?
是的 陛下
Yes, Your Majesty.
王后恳请陛下开恩
The Queen begs for mercy.
她供认自己由于贪享陛下的恩宠
She confesses that she was so desirous to be taken
沉迷王室的富贵
into Your Grace's favour, so blinded
窥图权柄的伟力
by desire for worldly glory,
而丧没了心智 惘顾了隐瞒旧情
that she did not consider how great a fault it was
欺君罔上 是何等大罪
to conceal her former faults from Your Majesty.
虑及妾曾决意
"Considering that I intended
倾此一生
"Ever during my life
对陛下忠贞诚实
"To be faithful and true to Your Majesty."
那么我们能够废免她的身份了吧
Then we can proceed with the annulment?
臣认为此举甚妥 陛下
I think it would be best, Your Majesty.
我不相信你在王后入宫之后
I don't believe that you didn't have carnal knowledge
未曾与其苟且偷情
of the Queen after her marriage to the King.
不要 我说的都是实话
Please don't! It is the truth
实因已有他人溺卧于王后闺帏
because someone else had succeeded me in her affections.
是谁
Who?
快说
托马斯·卡尔佩珀
Thomas Culpepper.
Thomas Culpepper?
国王的侍从
The King's groom?
没错
Yes, sir.
你对托马斯·卡尔佩珀熟悉吗
How well did you know this man, Thomas Culpepper?
相当熟悉 我曾与他嬉闹耍笑
Quite well. I flirted with him
并常在后梯处与他会面 还送过礼物给他
and met him sometimes by the back stairs, and gave him gifts.
他唤我作"可爱的小傻瓜"
He called me his "Sweet little fool."
你可与他行过苟且之事
And did you commit adultery with him?
没有 大人 绝未有过
No, my Lord. I never did
尽管罗彻福德女士曾鼓动我就范
although Lady Rochford encouraged me to do so.
罗彻福德女士鼓动过你吗
Lady Rochford encouraged you?
是的 她做过
Yes, she did.
然后她便散播这卑鄙的谣言
And then she spread a vile rumour
诬蔑说我们是爱侣 我们根本不是
that we were lovers, which we never were.
你承认你曾多次暗中
You don't deny that you met with the Queen
- 偷会王后 - 是的 大人
- in secret on many occasions? - No, my Lord.
但你否认与她通奸
But you deny that you ever committed adultery with her?
是的 我们从未逾越言语交流
I do. We never passed beyond words.
如果你不说实话 卡尔佩珀先生
If you don't tell me the truth, Mr. Culpepper,
你会被施以酷刑 直至你招认
you will be tortured till you do.
我说的是实话
I'm telling you the truth.
我也想有进一步发展
Which isn't to say I didn't want to go further!
我也想要与王后通奸 她也想
I intended and meant to do so with the Queen, and she with me.
上帝啊
My God.
光有这邪念就够得上叛国罪
That evil intent in itself constitutes high treason.
但那是凯瑟琳引诱我的
But it was Katherine who led me on!
是她想这样 不是我
She wanted it, not me.
还有她的侍女 罗彻福德夫人 是她策划的
And her servant, Lady Rochford, she provoked it
是她穿针引线 像那种妓院的老鸨
and acted as a procuress, like some madam in a brothel!
为什么他们都指责我 这不是我的错
Why are they blaming me? It's not my fault.
他们在王后的卧室幽会时 我得在外面望风
I had to stand guard when they met in the Queen's chambers,
甚至在她的厕所外望风
or even her stool closet.
我不想这样
I didn't want to.
我不喜欢这样
I didn't like doing it.
一次我不得不阻止国王进入王后的卧室
Once I even had to stop the King coming into the Queen's bedchamber,
因为卡尔佩珀已经在里边
because Culpepper was already there.
你认为他们有没有发生肉体关系
Do you think they had carnal knowledge at those times?
从他们的眉目传情间
I cannot think it otherwise,
答案毫无疑问是肯定的
considering all the things I heard and saw between them.
卫兵
Guard!
你觉得我会死吗 大人
Do you think I shall die, my Lord?
你觉得我会死吗
Do you think I shall die?
卫兵 开门
Constable! Open up!
陛下在调查之初就指示我
Your Majesty asked me at the beginning of this investigation
不到水落石出不可罢手
not to desist until I had got to the bottom of the pot.
陛下 恐怕我已触到真相
Majesty, I fear to say that I am already scraping the bottom,
陛下您的一位好伙伴
and a good companion of Your Majesty,
您信任的朋友
a fellow of trust,
看来已背叛了陛下您
seems certain to have betrayed Your Majesty
犯下了与王后 您的妻子通奸的大罪
committing adultery with the Queen, your wife.
是谁
Who is he?
您的侍从官 托马斯·卡尔佩珀
Your groom, Thomas Culpepper.
迄今为止 他们二人均否认此项控告
So far, both of them have denied the charges,
但他们都未否认曾密会多次
though neither of them denies the many illicit meetings
他们在随同陛下上次出访期间
they had on the backstairs and in the Queen's stool closet
曾在后楼梯及王后的卫生间密会
during Your Majesty's last progress.
罗彻福德夫人及其他几名王后陛下的侍女
Lady Rochford and other maids of Her Majesty have
均自愿提供物证以证明
come forward with corroborating evidence
他们之间有多次亲密接触
of their frequent intimacies.
还有 这封信是在卡尔佩珀的房间内搜到的
Finally, this letter was discovered in Mr. Culpepper's chambers.
是王后的笔迹
It is the Queen's handwriting.
她写道
She writes:
每每想起你不能常伴左右
"It makes my heart die to think
我便心碎不已
"I cannot always be in your company."
听闻您抱恙在身 恨不得胁下生翼
And, "I heard that you were sick and never longed so much
不顾一切见到你
for anything as to see you."
下面署名
And it is signed:
你至死不渝的
"Yours as long as life endures
凯瑟琳
"Katherine."
这一切都是你们的错
What has happened is your fault!
你们的错
Your fault!
是你挑唆我娶了她
You solicited me to marry her!
我怎会如此不幸 这般娶妻不慎
How misfortunate I am to have had so many ill-conditioned wives!
我发誓 不管那下作的贱人
I vow that any pleasure that wicked bitch got from
从淫乱中获得何种乐趣
her wantonness will be nothing-nothing
都抵不上我对她施之酷刑
in comparison to the pain she going to feel
所带来痛苦的万分之一
at the hand of my torturer!
辛苦了 夫人 我们给他起什么名字
Well done, wife. What shall we call him?
托马斯
Thomas.
很好 就托马斯吧
Very well. Thomas he is.
您还要继续审问罗彻福德夫人吗
You want to ask Lady Rochford some more questions?
- 是的 - 没必要了 托马斯爵士
- Yes. - There's no point, Sir Thomas.
罗彻福德夫人疯了
Lady Rochford has gone mad.
你去死
Death to you!
你们在这儿啊
There you are.
陛下 萨福克公爵大人到
Majesty? His Grace, the Duke of Suffolk.
你从不读圣经 是不是 查尔斯
You've never read the Bible, have you, Charles?
是的 陛下 我总让那些
No, Your Majesty. I've always allowed others,
比我更博学的人来念给我听
with more knowledge than I, to read it for me.
这么说来 你错过了许多警句格言
In that case, you've missed many great sayings and truths,
像所罗门卷里的这段 这里说道
Like this one here in the Book of Solomon, where it says:
妓女的嘴唇犹如蜂蜜
"The lips of a harlot are "a dropping honeycomb.
她的喉咙柔软赛油脂
"Her throat is softer than oil.
可到最后
"Yet in the end,
她却苦如苦艾
"she is as bitter as wormwood,
锋利赛过双韧之剑
and as sharp as a double-edged sword."
你所来何事
Why have you come?
弗朗西斯国王送来一封信
King Francis has sent you a letter.
信上怎么说
What does it say?
得闻王后淫邪不齿之行径
"I am sorry to hear of the displeasure and trouble which has been
所招致的不快与纷乱 我深表遗憾
caused "by the lewd and naughty behaviour of the Queen.
但深知我兄乃英明审慎
"But knowing my good brother to be a prince of prudence,
正直高尚之君王
virtue, and honour,
我希冀陛下 摆脱上述不快
"I do require him to throw off the said displeasure
明智而适度地 一如我这般
"and wisely, temperately, like myself,
勿需将您的荣耀置于女子的轻浮之上
"not reputing his honour to rest in the lightness of a woman,
而应置于上帝所赐之福祉
"but to thank God of all,
感激上帝仁慈所赐之安慰
"comforting himself in God's goodness.
女子之轻浮无法损毁男人之荣耀
"The lightness of women cannot bend the honour of men."
让弗朗西斯见鬼去吧
You tell Francis to go
告诉法王陛下
Tell His Majesty
我们对他的恳请不胜感激
that we are grateful for his solicitations.
是 陛下
Yes, Your Majesty.
迪尔罕和卡尔佩珀如何了
What of Dereham and Culpepper?
他们被控叛国了吗
Have they been arraigned for treason?
他们两人一同被审
They were tried together.
最后一刻 卡尔佩珀改口承认有罪
At the last moment, Culpepper changed his plea to guilty,
但两人都被判有罪
but both were found so.
他们被判在泰伯恩刑场施以绞刑 开膛和分尸
They are due to be hanged, drawn and quartered together at Tyburn.
告诉法官对卡尔佩珀减刑为斩首
Tell the judge to commute Culpepper's sentencing to beheading.
那迪尔罕更可恨
I hate Dereham more,
因为是他把王后姑息成这样
since he spoiled the Queen for me.
那罗彻福德夫人怎么样
Now, what of Lady Rochford?
她被查出犯有渎职与叛国之罪
She has been found guilty of misprision and treason
不过 鉴于她已精神失常
but, since she is insane,
不能处以极刑
she cannot be executed.
即刻让理查·李希在议会通过一项法案
You tell Richard Rich to pass a bill in Parliament
允许处决犯有叛国罪的疯子
making it legal to execute an insane person for treason.
清楚了吗
Do you hear?
遵命 陛下
Yes, Your Majesty.
朕错娶凯瑟琳·霍华德 你也难辞其咎
You were one of those who placed Katherine Howard in front of me.
此话不为过吧 公爵
Were you not, your Grace?
可有悔意
Any regrets?
退下吧 查尔斯
Charles.
告退 陛下
Majesty.
你们这些毫无廉耻的混蛋
You should be ashamed of yourselves!
卖国贼
Traitor!
"卡尔佩珀大人
"Master Culpepper,
我多想委身于你
"I heartily recommend me unto you,
又不知君心何意
"praying you to send me word how that you do.
我听闻你抱恙在身
"I heard that you were sick,
恨不得胁下生翼 不顾一切见到你
"and never longed so much for anything as to see you.
若你此时在我身旁
"I would you were with me now that you might see
便知我柔肠寸断 泣难下笔
"what pain I take in writing to you.
每每想起你不能常伴左右
"It makes my heart die to think
我便心碎不已"
"I cannot always be in your company."
恳请诸位为我祈祷
I beg you all to pray for me.
迪尔罕
"He, Dereham,
他赠予我许多爱的信物
"gave me lots of lovers' tokens.
他熟识一位伦敦的驼背小妇人
"He knew a little woman in London with a crooked back,
那妇人精通用丝绸制作花卉
"who was skilled in making flowers of silk,
他请那妇人做了法国茴香 并赠送与我
"who made for him a French fennel to give to me.
此后 新年时我又收到了心安草
"And later, a Heart's ease for a New Year's present,
还有一些薄绸 我拿来做了顶帽子
"and some sarcenet, which I had made into a quilted cap.
他一边唤我"爱妻"
"He called me "wife,"
一边抚摸我身体的私处
"and touched the secret parts of my body.
我记得曾回赠他衬衫的领和袖
"I remember I gave him a collar and sleeves for a shirt.
有一日
"And one day,
他抢走了我的一只银手镯
"he snatched a silver bracelet from me and kept it,
然后说 "爱妻 谢谢你的礼物"
"saying, Here, wife, a gift for me."
他常常热烈地激吻我
"And he kissed me often and so passionately
人人都说 他吻我多少次都不会厌倦
"that everyone said he would never have kissed me enough."
不
No!
凯瑟琳·霍华德
Katherine Howard,
你的婚前生活糜烂
you are indicted for having led an abominable,
卑劣 淫荡 放纵
base, carnal, voluptuous,
伤风败俗 与多人淫乱
and vicious life before marriage like a common harlot
堪比人尽可夫的娼妓
with several persons.
你以言行蛊惑 骗得国王宠幸
You led the King by word and gesture to love you,
隐瞒曾与弗朗西斯·迪尔罕交往之事
concealing your contract with Francis Dereham
严重威胁到王室血脉之纯正
to the peril of the King and his children begotten by you.
婚后
And after marriage,
你对迪尔罕格外关照
you showed the same Dereham notable favour,
同时勾引托马斯·卡尔佩珀 行苟且之事
while inciting Thomas Culpepper to carnal knowledge,
还对他说
telling him
你爱他胜过爱国王
you loved him above the King.
我来此带你
It is my duty
前往伦敦塔
to escort you to the Tower.
夫人
My Lady.
爱德华爵士
Sir Edward.
请别让他们带我走
Don't let them.
不
No.
托马斯
Thomas?
天啊
Oh God!
托马斯
Oh, Thomas!
- 夫人 - 不 不
- My Lady. - No, no, no, no!
天啊 托马斯
No, no! No, No! No, Thomas!
她被定罪了吗
Is she condemned?
是的 陛下
Yes, Your Majesty.
其他人呢
What of the others?
迪尔罕和卡尔佩珀被判处极刑
Dereham and Culpepper have been executed
法案已经议会通过
and the bill allowing a mad person to be executed
允许处死犯有叛国罪的疯子
for treason has become law.
我要开个宴会
I want to have a party.
这是受邀宾客名单
Here is a list of guests.
遵命 陛下
Yes, Your Majesty.
凯瑟琳·霍华德 你已被判处死刑
Katherine Howard, I have to tell you that you are going to die.
明早 即二月十三日清晨
You will be taken to your place of execution tomorrow morning,
将由枢密院派人押赴刑场
the 13th of February, escorted by members of the Privy Council.
可以提个要求吗
May I ask one favour?
可否给我一个垫头木
Will you bring the block to me
我想知道该如何摆放身体
so that I might know how to place myself
想熟悉一下
and... make trial of it?
如你所愿
As you wish.
还有其它需要吗
Is there anything else you need?
需要忏悔牧师吗
Do you want a confessor?
不用
No.
我很少对神祈祷
I have spoken to God so rarely,
恐怕他并不认识我
I did not think He would know who I was.
女士们
Ladies.
来点甜点吗
Something sweet?
你觉得怎样 陛下
What do you think? Your Majesty.
美丽的王后
Ah! A beautiful Queen.
夫人 有何遗言
Madam. Do you want to say a few words?
我恳请仁慈的国王
I ask forgiveness for my sins,
恳请神
from His Gracious Majesty,
恳请在场各位
from God,
宽恕我的罪过
and from all of you.
还能再说几句吗
Shall I say more?
不 夫人 已经够了
No, my Lady. That is already sufficient.
谢谢
Thank you.
时辰到了 夫人
It's time, my Lady.
我来此受死
I have come here to die.
夫人
Oh, my Lady!
我虽身为王后
I die a Queen.
但宁愿以卡尔佩珀妻子的身份死去
But I would rather die the wife of Culpepper...
生命何其美丽
Life is very beautiful.